Hey, I'm Dave. Welcome to Shop Talk,
where we answer all your week's best
questions, insights, and queries that
come in through the viewer comments, and
questions on the videos. Unfortunately,
I didn't make a video this week cuz I
was busy making the latest beta of the
new Task Manager, or a new task manager,
not the task manager, it's just a task
manager, and it's called Task Manager
OG. Glenn, how are you doing? I'll give
you a little demo of it if you're up to
it. Ah, I'm I'm doing I'm doing super,
Dave. I'm ruling the world. Oh, no.
That's what you said, I should say,
which was kind of a joke, but no, I'm
doing well, Dave.
>> Good. Good to hear it. So, I decided to
see what I could do to write a task
manager if I was going to do it with
today's hardware because the last time I
wrote this was in 1994 and, you know, a
486 or Pentium or something like that.
So, there was much less hardware. There
was no GPU, there was no direct 2D,
there was no direct composition. There
was nothing. So what you got was very
basic for the day but it became kind of
iconic. So I thought what could I do if
I decided to do it with today's hardware
you know using a couple% of the CPU not
100% of the CPU like 2% of the CPU or
something and some reasonable amount of
memor amount of memory. And so this is
what you got. This is the main page of
the task manager and it boots up to a
summary view which gives you meters for
your CPU clock uh temperature GPU. This
is on a Mac and on this Mac it can't get
the clock rate so it's just set to auto
because the system has control over it.
CPU overview gives you your uh CPU usage
here in the green line and your kernel
is the red line. Your thermals are the
orange line and your top end processes
depending on how much screen space you
have are listed here. And so rows that
change get a green background. You can
see as they come in and leave new ones
come in and they get filled in with a
green color and that fades out. It's
kind of a handy visualization
visualization.
And below that, we got memory
utilization. And then we have discs, we
have network, energy, GPU, NPU, and
thermals. Now, if I go to the
performance page, actually before I go
to the performance page, I should say
this is probably a little colorful for a
lot of folks. [laughter] Uh, I tend to
like really intense colors and I like a
lot of contrast, but I realize not
everybody wants that. So, if you go to
the colors picker here, you can actually
adjust the amount of saturation in the
user interface.
Seven is the default. Now, because I
like a lot of saturation, this one goes
to 11. Do you want to see it?
>> Uh, am I ready for it? I'm color blind,
so I can handle 11. No problemmo.
>> Okay, here it goes. What if you could
see color when I turn it to 11?
[laughter]
That' be funny.
>> I see I see some saturation, I guess, if
that's what you call it. Yep. And then I
can turn off the visual bloom
independently, which gives me just
really crisp high saturation lines,
which I kind of like.
>> I like that option to shut off the
visual bloom.
>> Yeah, sometimes it's nice depends on how
much saturation you got going on because
it does dim down with it. So if you turn
it down, you lose the visual bloom, but
much past seven, you start getting
blooming.
Uh, now there's other other schemes as
well. So first of all, I could have gone
into it and said I'm going to use light
mode.
And here we are light mode. So this is
if you're not into dark mode on your
Mac, this is what you would get. But
we'll go back to use system settings.
And I'm going to change the color scheme
to mono.
So if you don't want any color, you can
do mono. If you want classic green
phosphor, you can do green. If you want
classic amber. And if you want a blue
scheme that matches the midnight blue
theme that I happen to use in Visual
Studio, well, you're in luck because I
added a blue theme as well. So, we'll
put it back to color and we'll continue
out through the app here. Next page is a
performance page. Now, you can do your
one large graph of CPU or you can split
it out into each core. And these little
white trackers here on the right of
every graph, you'll see them in the main
graph here too, but on every one of
these little graphs, I stole that from
the Star Trek sick bay. um the original
series they had these little meters that
would go up and down with your heart
rate and systolic pressure or whatever
and I always
>> liked them as a kid so I stole them.
>> Another thing to notice too is on these
graphs you'll see the lines get closer
together as you go left and that's
because time compresses as you go left
which allows me to keep a lot of history
on screen but the right hand of the
graph is still fairly active and
scrolling fairly quickly.
Now on the performance page you've also
got a detailed memory graph with a whole
bunch of stats you may be interested in.
We've got a GPU page. It so shows the
GPU usage. Uh NPU, you'll see little
bursts of it occasionally. This one
actually tracks the share of hardware
blocks that are active because that's
about the most information I can get. So
it kind of goes 050.
It's not very granular.
>> Discs. You can also split this out into
separate discs. So, I see I have my
Apple SSD and I have uh some other SSD
and I have three Samsung PCI SSDs and a
Ninja Pro AV. This would be a SATA disc.
So, let me combine them again. And you
can do that with network adapters as
well, but I won't expand it. But, uh
that's the basics. Oh, thermals shows
you the share. Chrome is obviously
taking the bulk of the CPU or the
thermal energy right now. Task manager
is like a 14 relative to Chrome.
Thermals, you can go through and scroll,
check all your die temperatures, all the
different pickup points in the chip.
And processes view. I won't rat hole
here. This is very much like [laughter]
the ones in any task manager. You can
exp It's tree view though. So you can go
so you kill this and it'll kill
everything that Google has started. Or
you can go in and kill one window, which
I won't do because it might be the
important one. this might be the one you
need.
>> Right? So, [clears throat] I've got, you
know, the various applications that are
running right now and then I've got all
the background processes and I see those
separately. I've got a system info tab
which will populate now and give me all
the information about my system.
>> Who made my memory? Um, all my audio
stuff, who made that? What else is
interesting here? You know, you get your
Wi-Fi stats and find out what channel
you're on and all that kind of fancy
information. Can take a minute to go and
collect all the information. Let's see.
Here it goes. H. So, I'm on network
channel 37. Good to know.
Startup apps allows you to control what
things start up automatically with your
system, and you can just disable them by
unchecking their box. Users let you see
who is running what on your system. So,
if I say, oh, I want to find,
let's see,
Dave's clawed process. So I can then say
go to process details
or inspect
and this will give me all the
information about the process including
any network sockets it has open any
files it has open so you can check a
fair bit of detail
services same as you're accustomed to in
most task managers allows you start stop
kill services
>> and again all that stuff you've talked
about up to here is all in the free
version
it you get Yeah.
>> Yep.
>> Yeah.
>> Free. And if you want to pay for the
paid version, then you get the pro
features and that gives you things like
the power and frequency. So you go and
check the actual specific numbers. If
you want to check the smart data on your
disc, you can do that and find out, you
know, what the critical temperature is,
how many bits, bytes have been written
to it, written, read, so forth. We also
have benchmarks. And I'm going to show
you the T-mog score because that is a
unified score from zero to well 100
being the baseline and it's baseline to
an M2 Mac Pro Ultra for the Mac version.
It's based to baseline to a Ryzen AI395
plus Pro for the PC version and we
haven't decided what the baseline of two
for the Linux version yet. But here I'll
run it now. It's going to run a little
slower because I've got all kinds of
screen recorders and everything going on
for this podcast session. But I can
expect it to score somewhere near 100.
We would hope.
>> I like the dial adjustment.
>> Yeah, that took a while to get right to
get it to sweep in and have the gauge
look like you're shifting gears almost.
Now we'll do disc.
Yeah, I'm writing to disc. So, my disc
score is going to be terrible.
>> Yeah.
So, my score will be low because of
that, but we'll see.
>> 78. Yeah. And you see my disc score here
is 0.21 on right.
>> Yeah. [clears throat] I could actually
fix that by going and saying, "All
right, pick a different disc." And I'll
pick a different disc.
And I'll start this test again. What do
we get the first time? 1306. And now
we're getting 6,000. So,
>> if you pick a disc you're not otherwise
busy using, it goes much faster.
>> Did I miss or did it not show where you
I like I saw you hit the disc, but I
didn't see which disc you selected.
>> Uh, that may have popped up off screen.
>> Oh, that's why. Okay. Okay.
>> So, T-Mog score, we've got internet. I'm
going to do an internet test here.
Look at that. I'm on 5 GB internet, but
it's not usually full 5 gigabits. So,
>> yeah.
>> But 32 34
>> settle for Yeah.
>> Oh, it plummets. It's coming back. It's
coming back.
>> Yeah, it doesn't plumber. It plummets.
>> Plummets. Yes.
I spent a lot of time on this little VFD
font and you know the little grid behind
it to show you when the bits aren't lit
up and stuff to took some time.
>> What else we got? We got installed apps.
You can go through and figure out what
apps are using up the most space. Sort
by app size.
>> Uninstall apps pretty trivially. Disc
space. There's two modes here. Two modes
I should say. We'll start with balls.
And so the bigger balls represent your
biggest files. And once it stabilizes by
having done the scan, well, you can
already see this is probably the biggest
file. This is an MP4 in my Snagot
folder.
This is what is this?
Uh, NetBSD vax hard drive image. I need
that. You can grab a ball and move them
around. [laughter]
Entertain yourself. You can also switch
to block view which is very much like
the old defrag
>> and once it gets going it's kind of fun
to watch.
>> So that is the basics of the new task
manager. And you're saying how do I get
it? How do I get it for free? Well, it's
going into beta 2 and that should be
ready on Friday. So assuming you see
this on Friday, you can go to t-mog.org
tmog.org.
download it for free and you can't even
buy the full version yet because it's
not available for sale, but you can get
the beta and it remains in perpetuity
free for the non-pro features. So, give
it a shot. Let me know what you think
and if you've got feature suggestions,
please let me know because I'm just kind
of doing what I think would be cool, but
once it gets out in the hands of lots of
people, I'm sure you'll have even better
ideas that I can add to it.
>> There will be limitless requests and
suggestions, I suspect.
>> Yeah, I'm hoping. I mean, I can't do
them all, but I'll do the best ones.
>> And and many of them will be just on the
color and blooming and [laughter]
saturation alone, I suspect. Can you
move this? Why can't we move the screen
to that? And move all the little, you
know, diagnostics around and set them up
where I want them in the window and move
the taskbar from the bottom to the left.
>> Exactly. [laughter]
>> Well, that's why I try to make the UI
kind of customizable because I tuned it
not quite for me, but, you know, towards
the end of the spectrum that I like. And
so I figured that might be a little
strong for people. So given the ability
to change it and that kind of led to
different theming and it ran from there.
So
>> cool. Well, for this Oh, go ahead. You
got more stuff there, Dave?
>> No, I was going to say, why don't we
stop and then restart on the main
camera?
>> Sure. Sounds good. So,
>> yeah, we did the task manager thing. We
had a bit of a different episode this
time, Dave. Um, you didn't do Dave's
Garage, so we thought I'd throw in the
task manager stuff. Uh I've got a few
questions maybe from the last uh shop
talk episode, but most from the other
thing you did is you said, "Hey,
>> here's a bunch of stuff from your X
account. So uh I'm going to start with
some specific uh task manager stuff,
TMG, and then we'll move into some of So
again, you think you may have said this
sort of the start, but what what is task
manager OG and why did you decide to
rebuild such a familiar Windows tool?"
Now Dave,
>> well started with a friend of mine,
David. He was suggesting that you could
write Word with Claude. And I was like,
I don't think you could write Word yet.
And so we were debating that. I'm like,
you could probably write Task Manager.
And then that got me intrigued. And I
thought, why don't I try that? And of
course, you can't just say write task
manager. It'll do something. It'll it'll
be lame. So I wrote a spec, which was
107 pages of everything that you need to
know about Task Manager and what it does
in the world. And uh then I started with
that. And then my son came down with
appendicitis and he had to go into the
hospital and have surgery to have his
appendix removed which he did. And so I
was there for a couple of days. And then
he came home for a couple hours, started
bleeding internally and had to go back
to the hospital and be reoperated on and
get a blood transfusion. And so he was
in the hospital for the bulk of a week.
And so while I was in there, I needed
something to do with my new MacBook M5
Air. And I decided, hey, I'm going to
try coding Task Manager with AI assist
and see how it goes. And uh I'm not a
vibe coder per se. I like to be in
control of the code, but in this case, I
was more in control of the boundaries,
the APIs, the interfaces, and the
architecture. I let it write all the
grunt code, and then I did a lot of
reviewing and improving. But, uh, I was
really curious to see what I could do to
make it look cool today with today's
hardware because the GPU today, you
know, can render photorealistic scenes
at 120 Hz. So, it can certainly draw a
task manager at 60 Hz. And that got me
to thinking, well, task manager now
updates once a second. Activity monitor
is even slower. It's like once every two
seconds. So, what if I push the envelope
and go to 60 Hz refresh? So, everything
redraws 60 Hz, not at once per second.
Things like that. So,
>> so a couple questions to follow on.
Well, um, one is again earlier you said,
oh, I wanted to see, you know, and it
does take up some CPU, right? Takes up
some memory to run this. Um, so 2% 4%.
>> 1.5 on
>> Okay. And and what was the task manager
using in terms of CPU? That was
>> uh the I don't know. Oh, I do know
actually on Windows I was using about
1.5 and it was using about 1%.
>> Okay.
>> So
>> yeah,
>> it does use less CPU, but I mean I do
more before it gets out of bed than most
task managers do all day. So yeah, the
other thing I note too, uh, in the
original task manager, you spent a lot
of time making sure that, you know, the
when you scaled it or uh, and all the
drawing of all the effects was, what's
the word you use? Not um, flicker-free
basically, right?
>> You didn't have to do any of that now.
>> I didn't. And I don't know if it's
because it's just smart, if it double
buffered it, because things are so fast
now. It just draws off screen and then
does a frame swap at the end which
eliminates all flicker which would be
expensive but on today's computers it's
not too expensive. It's trivially cheap.
So
>> uh yeah I was surprised I didn't have to
do any fine-tuning for flicker. I did a
bit on the Linux version but it was
pretty easy to fix up.
>> Yeah.
>> But Windows and Mac came out of the box
pretty good. So,
>> and I'm using Direct 2D, Direct
Composition on Windows, and I'm using
Swift UI Kit on Mac and QT on Linux.
>> And Swift's a new thing for you, is it?
>> Yeah, I've never really written any
Swift code. I've tweaked Swift code now,
but I've never written any from scratch.
So, hey, I was just thinking if you're
not already subscribed to Dave's Addict,
now is a good time to go click the
subscribe button because I'm reminding
you to do it now. And if you're anything
like me, you won't remember to do it
anytime later based on memory. So, uh,
we'd appreciate it if you would
subscribe to the channel, get you here
next time when we have an episode, and
we'll see you then. Byebye.
>> So, the other thing I know you you
posted again today, I think I know it
was Facebook or X something that you you
said uh you just ran opened it up and it
just ran on the on Windows. So, did you
expect that Windows build to run on your
Mac through Wine or And what does that
tell you about the the project's
portability? Like,
>> well, it tells me two things. So, what
happened was I was building the website
for the for the beta and so I have the
Windows download and the uh Mac OS
download and the Linux coming soon link.
So, I'm in the browser. I'll test the
Windows and I click it, download it, run
it, and uh sure enough, it starts up,
but it looks a little weird because it's
actually running under Wine on my Mac. I
forgot I was on my Mac. I I got a, you
know, KVM built into the monitor and I
assumed I was on the PC,
>> but I wasn't. I was on the Mac and it
still ran. So, it told me two things.
one because
because the fact that it works and
everything works on wine, you can tell
task manager is not doing anything
secret that the wine guys don't know
about,
>> right?
>> People are going to wonder, well Dave,
are you using any of your secret
knowledge? And no, I'm really not. Um,
and that's kind of proof of that because
if it was secret, it wouldn't work in
wine. And what else does it tell me?
That it's pretty portable and that the
code is not too, you know, not too
clever for its own good because it just
works in wine. So, I think it's a pretty
good indication. [snorts]
>> The other thing that reminds me, so you
sent me a text today when I was at work
[laughter] and you said, uh, I thought
that's pretty funny. You said, "Hey, if
you get a moment, uh, you can test drive
the beta 2 in advance here. It's still
in progress, but works pretty well." And
I said, "I'll give it a roll once I get
home." Sure. And you said, "Oh, well, it
works on Windows, too, cuz I use Windows
at work." And I'm like, "Oh, my
machine's locked down." And then I said,
then I thought, "Well, what the hell?
I'll give it a try. See what it does."
Cuz it's not going to let me install
anything. So, I download it, run the
.exe, and then I sent you back a note.
Ha, I got a warning on my work machine,
but it'll let me run it anyway. No
install. It's just an .exe. And your
response was, I don't know. I never
installed it from a website. [laughter]
>> I have I have the own binary in my own
folder. I don't have to go to the
website to run it. So, [laughter] um,
and the only time I did was on a Mac
running the Windows version. So,
>> so it actually isn't an installed
application. It's just a an executable
>> for the beta. I probably will add a
wrapper because people [clears throat]
>> aren't especially used to downloading
executable and just running it.
>> Yeah,
>> I like that. I mean, just drag it
somewhere, put it where you want, but uh
>> Oh, I get a start menu shortcut that
way. Yeah, I used to we work with a ton
of files and stuff and I was doing this
whole thing where I need to rename and I
found a file renamer application
probably 20 years ago and it was just an
executable and it was fantastic cuz I
could run it and I didn't need to get
permission from it to install it and go
through that whole shenanigans and yeah
it was it was fantastic. So I was quite
surprised. Anyways, that was great. Um,
another one here. What useful visual
feedback have modern system monitors
lost since the blink and light uh and
1990s era?
>> Have they lost? Well, we don't get
access to individual registers anymore,
but that's probably not that useful
because nobody needs that for debugging.
On the PDP11, it can be incredibly handy
on a uh a modern CPU, not so much. So, I
guess we lost some of the granularity
and really deep level hardware control,
but we don't need or use it anymore. So
>> this is a conglomerate of a few I think.
Uh which task manager OG features have
drawn the strongest response so far? The
blinking disc, the pallets, block view
analysis, tear off panels, long history,
>> um the graphs and the front summary page
as being sort of a unified view of
what's going on on your computer without
having to tab through a whole bunch of
pages. Being able to see everything all
at once has been, I think, the most
wellreceived part of it.
>> Okay. I have a question about the long
history piece too. Um, so again it looks
like sort of the left half of the graph
is the compressed part and that
>> it goes one quarter is it 14 1/86th
132nd 164th. So it compresses that way
log two I believe.
>> So and that
>> you can adjust that in settings.
>> Oh you can. Okay. Yeah.
>> And that compression takes place over
the the time span that you have task
manager open or just while you're
actively looking at it
>> while it's running. Yeah.
>> While it's running. So I mean if you
leave it open for an hour, you're I mean
there's a ton of supercompressed
information, but I guess you're not
worried too worried about what happened
an hour ago anyway. So
>> No. And the thing is I fixed a bug in it
today. Not a bug, a shortcoming in the
architecture because what happened was I
left it running overnight.
>> That's what we call them now.
Shortcomings in the architecture. Okay.
Well, I mean, it was doing what it was
supposed to do, which is what we told it
to do. It was [clears throat] not the
efficient way to do it.
>> What happened was I left it running
overnight. Then I came in and it was
using a gigabyte of memory.
>> And normal task manager uses like a 100
megabytes of memory or something. And
this uses like 150 or something
normally. And a gigabyte was a lot.
>> So I thought, well, I'll have the AI see
if it can figure it out before cuz
debugging memory leaks is no fun,
especially in a running process. And
this process was the release version and
it didn't have debug symbols and had
been optimized.
>> So I gave it the process ID and I just
said have at it. Then I went and made a
coffee and I came back and it had tried
and failed to walk the memory of the
process on its own. And so then it used
the Microsoft SDK tool called VM map and
it had gone through and analyzed all the
memory that was being used by the
process figured out what that memory
would look like, what it was actually
containing and it realized well these
are the history buffers for all your CPU
data points for a graph going back 18
hours and I don't need to keep 18 hours
of history to draw that graph. So now I
start throwing away data much earlier
and I compress some of the tail data and
so on so forth. So it's much more
efficient on memory. Did you in you I I
mean you intentionally left it running
overnight. Was that with the purpose of
trying to see what happened or
>> Well, make sure it didn't crash or
anything.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, that was a nice little
discovery that Yeah. wouldn't reveal the
same time like memory leaks. So,
>> cool. Okay. So, I think that's it for
the task manager stuff for now. So, then
we're like, how do we build this
episode? Um and it's interesting. I um I
think I had mentioned last time about uh
collecting uh a list of ideas from
previous shows cuz you're you're off to
take one of your kids to college
tomorrow and you're off next week so we
won't have an episode. So I just
happened to go on to YouTube today and
there's a comment um that someone left.
So this comes from Narcissus says Glenn
you mentioned in this video you're going
to go through previous videos to capture
possible suggestions for future videos.
I don't know where you are personally
with using AI or if you're currently
using it for your work in this channel,
but it would be a great beginner's
project to feed those 15 plus videos or
comment sections into AI and use an
agent to scan them and organize a list
for you. Uh yeah, [laughter] that's what
I did. Like I did it yesterday. So I
think I I went back and collected the
comments from every episode of Dave's
Garage and Shop Talk this year. So about
64 episodes. It was over 7,500 comments.
put it into AI and you and I were
facetiming last night and the results
came back and I think [laughter] I sort
of went all giddy when I saw it. It
actually created like four tabs in the
worksheet and all the listen and the
summary and I was just like stoked for
all this data that it pulled out. So,
I'll be uh weedling through that stuff
over the next few uh few days or couple
weeks while you're gone. So, um yeah.
So, I thought that was kind of a neat
segue into using that for this. So,
>> yeah, that's cool. Uh so now we got
another sort of a general question here
from stuff. So does AI replace the
research and debugging work or does it
make an experienced person dramatically
faster? Just makes an experienced person
dramatically faster. Um I'm not doing
much or any other debugging myself, but
I'm telling the AI what I think is wrong
based on my experience in the industry.
And I like to believe that gives it a
real leg up in not only finding the
problem, but in fixing it appropriately
instead of just flailing and adding, you
know, it'll just go crazy adding
instrumentation and debug strings hoping
to spot a reason if you don't tell it
and it can't see why the code is
misbehaving. So any hints you can give
it, all the better.
>> Okay. [snorts] And and another one
that's sort of a general here based on
that result you found from leaving Task
Manager run overnight. Now, that's not
an uncommon way to find problems or
discover potential bugs or what would
you call it uh uh architecture system
architectural deficiencies in system
architecture. Uh so how would you have
diagnosed that in the old days with a
debugger or heapwalk allocation tagging?
Yeah, you'd uh attach a debugger to it
and you'd find out in the heap where all
the memory was and you'd find out in
this case it's in the Windows uh
fragmentation or small fragmentation
heap for small allocations and then
you'd walk that and go what kind of data
am I looking at then if it's got strings
and text in it then you know what you're
looking at and otherwise if it's a
structure you've got to figure out what
kind of memory structure you're looking
at but in my case they were all buffers
from the history for these graphs and so
I would have eventually hoped to
recognized them as such and then saw
that oh yeah I've got you know 100
thousand of them in memory at this
point. Um but it' be way more more
manual and painful to do it in the old
days.
>> Yeah. And when you posted it you said oh
yeah like this would you walk in and saw
this is like I know how I'm spending my
entire day. Yeah. So
>> this bug that it sorry the deficiency in
the system architecture [laughter] it
helped you with
>> would do you have a sense of how long
would that have taken you four hours a
day more than a day to
>> having seen the fix it that would be a
couple hours.
>> Okay. Okay.
>> It wasn't as gnarly as it could be.
>> Whether I was smart enough to see it as
easily as the AI did I don't know. But
the actual problem wasn't
>> uh a really sinister one. It was pretty
obvious once you had the tools and the
investigation to see what was going on.
>> That's not so bad. So your third cup of
coffee, you would have had it kind of
figured out.
>> Oh yeah, [laughter]
>> a couple bruises on your head. Another
generic one. So what what did the during
this process with the the task manager?
What what did the AI actually infer and
which tools did it use and which
conclusion still required sort of your
judgment? Where was the the diamond Dave
input on this?
>> Well, in terms of how it looks, that's
100% me. I didn't say vibe go to task
manager. I said I want this box here and
I want this color. I want round corners.
And I I wrote the VFD meter bars kind of
by hand and I had to draw rectangles and
I went in and tuned it from there with
the bloom inside and outside.
>> Whoa. You could draw rectangles.
>> No, I made it draw the rectangles. So I
just added a bloom on the inside and
outside. [laughter]
Um [clears throat]
so I did a lot of that and I did all the
visual layout and told it exactly what
to put where and how it should behave.
And then I let it worry about the
details of how to make that happen.
>> The VFD is nice.
>> On them, so you know, it doesn't go
doesn't jump from here to here. It
slowly goes and fades back like an old
VFD meter would.
>> Yeah. So, was was it uh really a leak?
And is 1 gigabyte reasonable for 18
hours of performance history?
>> No, it wasn't really a leak. It was
intentional.
>> And no, it's not reasonable. I mean, it
depends. Yeah, it's reasonable. You've
got gigabytes upon gigabytes of memory
and near infinite disk space. So if it
takes a gigabyte every 12 hours or 18
hours, it's not the end of the world.
But it's a bug because it doesn't need
to have anywhere near that amount of
data to draw the graphs I'm drawing. So
>> another one here. So when did you write
the original task manager and how did
dog fooding Windows NT help shape it?
>> Uh November 94, I think, is when his
birthday is. And so once I brought it in
and we stuck it in the build then, yeah,
then you get tons of feedback.
Everybody's got an opinion on how it
should work and everybody breaks it, you
know, figures out how to where the weak
points are. And so unfortunately, it was
in pretty good shape by the time I
checked it into the build, but uh and it
was wellreceived, but yeah, it's a tough
tough crowd. And then another one here.
Was BSD top on real PDP11 hardware the
inspiration and did that influence task
manager OD's visual personality at all?
>> I don't know. I think so. Not OD or OG.
Okay. Um
>> well I suppose the top processes looks a
lot like top doesn't it?
>> Right.
>> Um so I guess in that sense it did. I
mean are there other ways to draw a list
of processes other than PID name and CPU
use and memory? I probably there are but
that's pretty standard. So that may go
back to top a PS minus ax at the shell
which is basically what top does only in
an animated fashion is probably the
original um cuz I had a book on Unix
system 5 release 4 and they showed how
to use the ps command to dump the
process table what was running and all
that and I thought that was super cool
and that was my first exposure to it I
guess. Uh, and then another one here.
What was the dual MIPIPS development
workstation like? And why was the visual
uh C++ MIPS port painful?
I was using it quite a bit and reporting
bugs, but I didn't do any of the work on
the port. I just let them know what
worked, what didn't work, and you know
what my repo case was for making it not
work. So, I wasn't debugging Visual
Studio. I was debugging a lot of shell
code on the MYIPS. And it's not the
worst. So, I actually kind of like the
MEIPS instruction set. Some of the other
ones that have, you know, if you got a
delayed branch instruction where it
actually continues working for a couple
instructions after you jump. I don't
know if you've ever seen this, but what
happens is, say you've got a go-to in a
basic program. Well, go to takes some
time. While it's figuring out where to
go to, you could do two more things. So,
you put two more statements after it and
it still runs them.
>> Stuff like that. And so it's hard when
you're debugging and looking back at
code up the stack to deduce exactly what
happened. And um it's not bad if the
code's not optimized, but once it's
optimized, it gets pretty ugly.
>> Um the MIP's dual processor machine was
was great for the time because I think
the alternative was like a P100 or maybe
a P200 at the time was the fastest
machine you could get. So dual 100 MHz
MIPS cores was
>> right
>> pretty fancy. How important was Mark
Leovski in championing Task Manager and
where did the wind uh 9x era resistance
come from?
>> Initially what happened was I put task
manager in the build and Dave Cutler
said put it on the start menu. So I put
it at the top of the start menu. Now
that's like [laughter]
I haven't got a good analogy for you but
it's kind of like being on your front
lawn and putting a new
>> decoration up there. You know,
>> did Dave think you were infantry and he
was moving you to the front line? Yeah,
you go take the
>> take the shells. [clears throat] Yeah.
[laughter]
>> Um, so the W95 guys were not impressed
and and rightly so. So they pushed back
pretty hard and so we moved it down to
system tools.
>> But uh that maybe gave them some bad
feelings about it because they thought
it was too nerdy and had too many nerd
knobs and too techy and they didn't want
any part of it and they didn't care
about it on Windows NT but
>> they didn't want anything like it on 95
and
>> they were giving us some gumption. So
Mark L was really a champion of
defending it both internally and NT to
make sure it got included and done and
then shielding me from
>> the uh nonsense from abroad.
>> I don't I don't remember when you did
that great interview with Dave Cutler
asking about he didn't say and you
didn't ask why he oh just put it on the
start menu was that
>> I was going to call him on that. No, but
he wouldn't have said that flippantly.
Like it would have been
>> I don't think he gave a about the
start menu.
>> Oh,
>> that's a UI problem. He's a colonel guy,
right? He's like, "Yeah, you click on
your little pretty pictures on the
desktop,
>> right? Just put it there so we can get
to it."
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> Don't hide it under a bunch of other
stuff. Just put it where we need it.
There it is. Yeah. Someone else will
figure that out. Okay.
>> I think that's it mostly. Yeah.
>> Ah, okay. Cool. How did a temporary 1994
format dialogue and an arbitrary
decision about cluster slack turned into
Windows lasting 32 GB FAT formatting
limit?
>> Oh yeah, I do. I've done an old episode
on this, but uh what happened was I was
writing the format dialogue for Windows
because it didn't have one because it
was completely different than Win 95.
>> And I did a temporary UI where I just
laid out bang bang bang bang bang, you
know, the controls in the format
dialogue that they're just top to
bottom. No elegance, no UI design, no
sensibility. And I figured somebody with
design touchibility will come along and
lay this out and make it look pretty.
But no, it's been 30 years and looks
exactly like it did the morning that I
just
>> copy pasted the controls down in a
column. But the problem with FAT 32 is
you only have so many clusters on a
disc. And the bigger that disc gets, the
bigger those clusters get. And the
bigger a cluster gets, the more sectors
are in it. And so you can have dozens,
hundreds, thousands of clusters or of
sectors in a cluster. And the problem is
if you use one bite, you use an entire
cluster,
>> right?
>> So let's say your cluster is like
>> 32k.
>> So every file that is any size under 32k
takes up 32k and it winds up wasting a
lot of space. So, the bigger the disc,
>> um, you really don't want to use fast 32
on big discs because of that. Now, if
you're only saving one or two files cuz
it's like in a video camera and you've
got an SD card,
>> well, I didn't foresee that cuz who
would have thought of 32 GB files at the
time? But,
>> um, nowadays it makes some sense, but at
the time, we really wanted to discourage
you from formatting drives in that
format at at a certain size. And so, we
just said we'll pick a limit and we'll
do 32.
>> Yeah. because that above that your
clusters get so big it's really
wasteful. Yeah. So,
>> okay.
>> And my common scenario there was MP4s on
a flash disc was really
>> the most common type of thing in there,
you know, a couple megabytes and so on
or MP3s I should say, not MP4s, but
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Was scan disk really
written in pure x86 assembly? And why
was that the right choice at the time?
>> Uh, I assume it was the right choice
because it worked. It was written by
Richard Jernigan who was the employee
and he was in the office next to me when
I was an intern
>> and so he wasn't that much older than me
but he knew a whole lot about Windows or
about MS DOS MS DOS programming so I
would sit in his guest chair and pepper
with him questions and distract him
needlessly and endlessly and he was
pretty good humored about it and I
learned a lot but watching him was
impressive because he was he was coding
scan disk and the entire UI framework
that scan disk runs under in pure x86
assembly and all the disk interface
based stuff and you know the disc
scanning and file system correction and
it's a oneman show. It was quite an
impressive
impressive turn I should say.
>> That was like uh you and our classmates
in uh grade nine computer science class
watching you [laughter] coding in
hexadesimal. We're like we're learning
basic and you're typing in A's and E's
and Fs and Yeah.
>> Somebody had to do it.
>> Different. Yeah. Different world. What
was it actually like to dog food
bleeding edge NT builds and live with
the blue screens? It says at home, but I
I suspect a lot of them at work, too.
>> Yeah, work was worse. I wouldn't bring
home a build until it reached IDW
usually, which was our internal
developer workstation quality
designation, which meant it's good
enough to use on your desktop. And so
that would be every couple weeks a new
IDW build would come out. But daily
builds would come out and you would run
them all on your build machine. And so
you would be running a a build that's a
couple weeks old maybe on your dev
machine. And that's what I'd be running
at home too. And my wife, bless her, she
had to run it on her machines, too,
because I'm like, well, we're all going
to be company people here. And so her
machine would just be bug checking all
the time trying to get work done and
blue screens. And
>> I was just I wanted to make sure I
mentioned that. I'm glad you brought
that up because I'm like, how did your
wife feel about that? Because yeah,
[laughter] I think you mentioned sport.
>> Still is a good sport. Um, so for years
I ran beta builds at home at all times
and so now I don't I, you know, I'm not
a early adopter on systems. Now I'm not
the kind of guy who's I got to get it
the morning it comes out. Now I'll wait
a couple weeks.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Uh, we got a question here
from Wayne Arnold.
>> Uh, he says, "In the early 80s, I was
working for automatic data processing.
We eventually had IBM OS2. The 16-bit is
their enterprise desktop operating
system and then they updated to Warp in
1994." He said, "Did Microsoft ever see
IBM's OS2 or Warp OS as a threat to
Windows NT?"
>> Not to NT. I think they might have seen
OS2 initially as a threat to their
dominance in MS DOS. And of course
that's why they had their hand in there
with IBM. But eventually when Windows
3.1 took off and the user interface
started doing so well they knew they
kind of had the golden goose I think and
they were just eager to get out of that
marriage which they did and let IBM take
the OS2 part with them. And nothing
wrong with OS2, but people had fallen in
love with the Win31 interface. And so
scaling that on top of an industrial
quality operating system with that
interface and then later with a Win 95
interface was a good mix.
>> Uh, another question from Cal 2127 says,
"How much Windows NT subsystem uh for
running OS2 apps could be ported to
modern NTbased OSS?"
>> I don't know. There's still the OS2
subsystem, but that's only on old
Windows. It's long since been removed.
I'm pretty sure there has been no OS2
subsystem still shipped with NT for
quite some years. I'm not not sure on
that, but
>> yeah, he says, "I'd love to see an HLE
emulator to allow Oils 2 applications to
run."
>> Well, one guy you want to look up is
Virtually Fun on X. uh his tag, you
know, at virtually fun and he's always
doing cool things like the Pix subsystem
and the NT subsystem and the OS2
subsystem and getting old software to
run and getting pinball to run on a MIPS
and all kinds of crazy stuff. So, if
you're into that era of stuff, he's a a
good person to follow. And uh as for X,
I know it's not everybody's cup of tea,
but I'm trying to stay kind of neutral.
I don't I don't do the political takes.
I'm trying to do just computer stuff. So
follow me on X if you're uh interested
in the daily shenanigans.
>> Daily shenanigans. Kind of like what we
do weekly here. Shenanigans.
>> Dave Pale 1968. If you're looking for
me.
>> Yeah. What was it like opening Arch with
Hyperland uh Omari for the first time
and having to discover even the basic
controls.
>> It's very [laughter] confusing. I had to
get Chachi Pat out. I'm like what do I
do? and it says, "Well, press control K
or command start K." And that's the the
Windows or the Mac key depending on
which system you're on. And uh then you
get a menu of other keys. Oh, start a
terminal. It's super enter. That's what
it is. Super key. So super enter does
this and super W and super Tiles
windows. And so you start to pick up
these things as you go. But this is an
operating system made for people who
don't use a mouse. And I'm a mouse guy.
I hated the mouse when the mice when
mice first came out. I was like, "No,
I'm not a wimp. But no Windows icon
mouse pointer stuff for me.
>> But uh now I'm pretty proficient with it
and so I don't need a keyboard only
inter interface. But as an OS it seems
very cool and lean and fast. So I'm sure
you can be hugely productive with it if
you adjust to the hyperland ways.
Hyperland being the window manager
system on top of Linux that they're
using.
>> Okay. Uh another one here. What
surprised you most when you got the
tools SSH in your own projects compiling
despite never having used Arch?
>> Um, I was impressed that not much had to
change.
>> So I thought Arch is going to be, you
know, significantly different than
Debian, but I had to figure out how to
use Pac-Man instead of AP but or apt.
But Pac-Man is the package manager. Let
you like install your compiler and
install git and install the tools. A lot
of it comes with system, but a lot of it
doesn't yet. So
>> yeah. Yeah. So, how can Task Manager OG
feel native on Windows, Mac, and Linux
without becoming three unrelated
products? And I know you have to vary
them a little bit, but maybe that's the
thing. How do you vary them to make them
fit in each system, but keep them all
the same or similar?
>> It's kind of a weird architecture. At
the top, you've got the user interfaces,
and so that's written in Direct 2D for
Windows, and as I mentioned, UI kit for
Mac and then QT for uh Linux. And then
they all talk to a common C++ core and
then that core branches out to system
specific helpers for things like stuff
that you can only do on a Mac or the
getting the process information is
different on you know Windows, Mac and
Linux. So
>> and then what's that one tool you have
the uh sorry I can't see it the clock I
guess and you said you can't access it
on the Mac but it still stays there.
It's just not showing information I
guess that's another
>> the clock. Which one are we talking
about here? uh when you were running it,
it's got the CPU, then the clock, then
the temp.
>> Oh, that's the clock speed. So, on a
Windows machine and on some Macs, you'll
see the actual CPU uh megahertz or
gigahertz
>> bouncing up and down.
>> So, it tracks that pretty accurately,
but on this machine, it just says it's
auto. We don't tell you.
>> Oh, it's just on that machine, not all
max. Ah, okay. Okay. Now, the other
thing you said, so we're sort of going
to give some credit to your son for his
appendix and the following problem
because that's what provided you the
gift of time
>> to work on this. But you also It was on
your Did you get a new uh laptop as
well?
>> I did. I got a MacBook M5. Here it is.
>> Ah.
So, how new is that bad boy then?
>> About 3 weeks now.
>> Oh. Oh, okay. Wow.
>> It's funny. It's now my fastest machine.
It's faster than my Mac Pro because my
Mac Pro is an M2 Ultra. Now, it's not
faster. F multi-core and compiling big
projects, but for single core tasks, the
M5 is a pretty snappy chip. So,
>> holy cow. So, you've been riding that
thing hard in the last 3 weeks then with
this task manager stuff, eh?
>> So, you want you wonder what I did
yesterday?
[laughter]
>> Uh, well, even if I don't want to know,
let's tell everybody.
>> All right. So, I bought a new Mac, a Mac
Studio on eBay.
There's a couple people listing Mac M3
Ultras with whatever it is, 30 24 cores
or 32 cores, the full boat and 80 GPU
cores and 512 GB of memory and 8 terb of
SSD.
Now, this sounds like a ludicrous spec,
but they were sending these machines out
to YouTube influencers 6 months ago.
They offered to send me four of them.
Actually, they were four 128s to make a
512. And [snorts]
uh I didn't really like the terms. I
don't really do sponsored episodes, so I
declined. But I know a lot of people
have got them. And so I think they're
now entering the secondary market. But
I'm pretty sure this is not that. I'm
pretty sure this is a scam. But I want
to know what the scam is. And so I just
bought it that I made sure I had eBay
power, you know, eBay e eBay buyer
protection. Okay.
>> And then the PayPal protection. And it's
on my MX, which I got some protection
there. So, between those three layers,
of course, we'll all probably point
fingers at each other, but ideally I'll
be protected. And it's supposed to be
here tomorrow, and unfortunately, I'm
not around.
>> Oh, man.
>> Now, here's the trick. The guy that I
bought it from sent me a thing saying,
"Oh, it's going to take an extra day to
ship. I'm really sorry. I'm going to
send you a free poster, and I gave you
$50 refund."
Which makes no sense whatsoever.
a free
>> I think he's gonna do [snorts]
>> I'm guessing it's going to be a poster
of a Mac M3 Ultra probably.
>> Okay.
>> And uh
>> a Countach. I don't know.
>> Yeah. No, it'll probably be a picture of
the computer that I bought.
>> Okay.
>> And then he can say, "Oh, look. I got
delivered
>> and I'm not going to sign for it unless
I open the box and find an N3 Ultra Mac
inside." So
>> Ah.
And the $50 back, is that some sort of
thing?
I don't know how he works that to his
advantage.
>> And what's the
>> or it's like a $30,000 Mac for three
grand and he was really sorry about it
shipping it late and I got 50 bucks off.
>> How much are they asking for?
>> 30 grand.
>> Wow.
>> You know, or maybe it's gray market and
it can never be activated and you can't
install an operating system on it. Maybe
it's stolen and the cops will raid me as
soon as I connected to the internet. I
have no idea what the catch is yet, but
I was so intrigued. I have to find out.
>> Yeah. And you're flying out of town when
the thing's supposed to arrive.
[laughter]
That'll be one of the kids problems when
it arrives and the cops come to the
door. Yeah,
>> that's right.
>> You'll be somewhere else watching on the
>> Yeah. watching on your uh UniFi system
going. Couple last ones here. After
rebuilding Task Manager and trying
modern Linux, what old Windows component
would you most like to uh tackle next?
It's a good one.
Old Windows. Calculators are fun, but
the world does not need another
calculator.
Zip has been done.
What's an old tool? I don't know. Give
me a suggestion in the video comments
because that'd be a fun project to take
some old tool and make it modern. I
mean, that's kind of what I'm doing with
Task Manager, but it's certainly not the
only example of something you could do.
So,
>> yeah. And I think also say over the next
uh week or two, I'm going to try and put
a couple little polls or something and
post some of this uh episode ideas that
I can collect from the stuff and post it
on the community channel on Dave's Attic
and see if we can get something going
there, too. So, we'll do that. Uh, what
does the 1969 Pontiac 2 plus2 teach you
about why old mechanical interfaces
still feel so good? Or maybe you want to
talk about your Continental one, too. I
know you've been goofing around. Not
goofing around. Um, you have an extra
dash display for it that you've been
doing some stuff with
>> for my Continental. I'll tell you the
Continental story. Just a random
tangential here, but I've got a spare
dashboard for instrument cluster for it.
And the dash lights are kind of a nice
dim green in the car and you can only
see it when there's no lights and so
they really could be a lot brighter. I
thought maybe the Rio staff's dirty. So,
I I got this new dash. I wired it
straight to 12 volts and nah, it's still
dim as it's annoyingly dim. So, I
thought, I've got green LED 194 bulbs,
194 being the bulb that plugs into the
little socket. And I did that and it
looked pretty good. And I thought, but
what if they were brighter yet? So, I
went on eBay and I'm like, what can I
get from China? And so, I found Lays
Fit, which I've uh
>> because you were just itching to pay
some more tariffs, right?
>> Absolutely. If you can't pay twice the
price, it's not as nice. And so, I uh
ordered a bunch of Lays Fit Green Laser
194 bulbs and put them in the dash and
they are wicked bright. And fortunately,
they are dimmable, so I can dim them
down. They go as bright as you want to
go pretty much.
>> They'll light your shop, right?
>> The other thing I did is I bought a blue
light or ultraviolet flashlight. You
know, like where they go on
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> hotel room. Yeah. [laughter] Where Wilfr
Rimley strangled Robert Crane with
oatmeal.
>> It's a long story. [laughter]
>> Well, you're just saying that cuz I had
my first oatmeal in 25 years last
Saturday. But yeah,
>> so I got this light and I realized what
if they use UV reactive paints on the
dash.
>> Oh.
>> So I got the light to test it and the
needles,
they just go super intense, but the
numbers are dark.
>> Oh.
>> So if they had used, you know, a white
fluorescent paint on the gauge numbers,
the gauges and the scales are all
beautiful, but you can't see the
numbers. So
>> Oh, wow.
It's like those women uh they were
making it there was the radium infused
paint and they Oh yeah. Licking the
brushes
>> and then my jaw fell off.
>> Was that for watches? That was watches
and instruments, wasn't it?
>> Yeah. Painting the the tridium or
whatever they would paint. I think it
was tridium, not radium, but uh
>> Okay.
>> Radium in those days for all I know, but
tridium for sure. And painting it on the
hands of watches and stuff.
>> Excellent. Yep. There's a good job. Um,
that's episode 91.
>> Well, hey, thanks for joining us out
here in the shop today. Try joining for
Shop Talk. We'll be here in a week or
two, same time, same place, same
channel. Make sure you're subscribed.
Maybe turn on the bell notification icon
because you'll forget and then the bell
will remind you when we come back. So,
thanks. And until then, we'll see you
next time right here in Dave's garage.
Good night.
Which is actually Dave's attic, but
that's okay.
>> [laughter]
>> I was going to say something like that.
No,
>> you haven't done that for a while.
That's been probably
6 months since you've done that. So,
>> done what?
>> Dave's garage.
>> Oh, really? Yeah. I try to get it
straight, but my cadence was off. We're
now recording.
I feel obligated to talk.
>> I can cut.
>> I can't look at the camera and the thing
at the same time.
>> Yeah, that's fine. I don't have to show
your face. I can show me going.
Oh, that's amazing.
That's fantastic, Dave. Why wouldn't
anybody pay $199.95 for the pro version
per month?
>> Wait, wait. It's not $1.99. [laughter]
>> Yeah. Yeah. We got special deal this
month. Yeah.
>> It's only 49. How much you pay?
>> Three easy payments. Yeah. Three easy
payments. $49.95.
Yeah. And then after that, it's only
$4.95 per month. I'm charged in advance
in 10-year increments.
>> I'm joined as always by my co-host
Glenn. Glenn, how are you doing today?
>> I'm awesome, Dave. I'm ruling the world
>> or whatever you say in Norway.
>> Yeah,
that might be your coke self. I don't
know. [laughter]
>> Oh, can you tell?
It was like super obvious, but I guess
just never
>> Yeah. My autism, we never knew what the
hell it was. You know, once you see it,
you're like, "Oh, yeah.
>> It was obvious to everyone but you." So,
yeah.
>> Yeah. But nobody said anything. So,
>> yeah. It's easier cuz I mean, my madeup
story is way better than the truth
anyway. So, why would you ruin that?
>> I'm happy. Boy, I'll never touch that
again. [laughter]
Lesson learned.
>> Yeah.
>> Something goes wrong, I'm parking it
with a bottle of wine on the seat and
the key is the ignition. That's it.
>> Yeah. No one's getting a chance to tell
you again. Yeah.
>> I don't think anybody's ever got them
back in. They probably just total the
car.
>> You're the Yeah. bottle of wine. Well,
that's how you got the car, right? You
just saw it with a bottle of wine
sitting in it. [laughter]
>> Yeah. A lot of organizing going on. I'm
probably going to screw it up halfway
through the recording, but that's okay.
cuz I know the editor. [laughter]
>> There you go.
>> Yeah. [snorts]
>> For peripheral neuropathy, I guess it
would be.
>> Oh, okay. That's like neuropathy at the
edges.
>> Yeah, at the end.
[laughter]
>> I can hear myself. That's weird.
Can I still Oh, I can hear it in your
room because your audio is disconnected.
You're on speakers.
>> Am I?
>> I am. Zero. [groaning]
>> All right. Are you ready?
>> Yes, sir.
>> This Frank Franklin's a turtle. See?
Who's the engine?
>> The British thing that
>> Ringo Star Thomas the engine.
>> Thomas the tank engine. Yeah.
>> Oh, he's a tank engine. Wow.
>> I'm more of a Henry myself.
>> Henry the
>> steam locomotive. Oh,
>> okay.
He's like the power of 10 locomotives.
It's
>> Yeah.
>> Self-evident.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
>> So,
>> yeah. Start the show, Dave.
>> Okay. [laughter] Here we go.
>> This little chair will be waiting for
one of you and a rocking chair for
another who likes to rock and a big
armchair for [music] two to curl up in.
All next time right here on Shop Talk.